IX

An hour passed, and the downstairs rooms at the hotel grew dim and were almost deserted, while the little box-like squares above them were brilliantly irradiated. Some forty or fifty people were going to bed. The thump of jugs set down on the floor above could be heard and the clink of china, for there was not as thick a partition between the rooms as one might wish, so Miss Allan, the elderly lady who had been playing bridge, determined, giving the wall a smart rap with her knuckles. It was only matchboard, she decided, run up to make many little rooms of one large one. Her grey petticoats slipped to the ground, and, stooping, she folded her clothes with neat, if not loving fingers, screwed her hair into a plait, wound her father’s great gold watch, and opened the complete works of Wordsworth. She was reading the “Prelude,” partly because she always read the “Prelude” abroad, and partly because she was engaged in writing a short Primer of English Literature—Beowulf to Swinburne—which would have a paragraph on Wordsworth. She was deep in the fifth book, stopping indeed to pencil a note, when a pair of boots dropped, one after another, on the floor above her. She looked up and speculated. Whose boots were they, she wondered. She then became aware of a swishing sound next door—a woman, clearly, putting away her dress. It was succeeded by a gentle tapping sound, such as that which accompanies hair-dressing. It was very difficult to keep her attention fixed upon the “Prelude.” Was it Susan Warrington tapping? She forced herself, however, to read to the end of the book, when she placed a mark between the pages, sighed contentedly, and then turned out the light.

Very different was the room through the wall, though as like in shape as one egg-box is like another. As Miss Allan read her book, Susan Warrington was brushing her hair. Ages have consecrated this hour, and the most majestic of all domestic actions, to talk of love between women; but Miss Warrington being alone could not talk; she could only look with extreme solicitude at her own face in the glass. She turned her head from side to side, tossing heavy locks now this way now that; and then withdrew a pace or two, and considered herself seriously.

“I’m nice-looking,” she determined. “Not pretty—possibly,” she drew herself up a little. “Yes—most people would say I was handsome.”

She was really wondering what Arthur Venning would say she was. Her feeling about him was decidedly queer. She would not admit to herself that she was in love with him or that she wanted to marry him, yet she spent every minute when she was alone in wondering what he thought of her, and in comparing what they had done to-day with what they had done the day before.

“He didn’t ask me to play, but he certainly followed me into the hall,” she meditated, summing up the evening. She was thirty years of age, and owing to the number of her sisters and the seclusion of life in a country parsonage had as yet had no proposal of marriage. The hour of confidences was often a sad one, and she had been known to jump into bed, treating her hair unkindly, feeling herself overlooked by life in comparison with others. She was a big, well-made woman, the red lying upon her cheeks in patches that were too well defined, but her serious anxiety gave her a kind of beauty.

She was just about to pull back the bed-clothes when she exclaimed, “Oh, but I’m forgetting,” and went to her writing-table. A brown volume lay there stamped with the figure of the year. She proceeded to write in the square ugly hand of a mature child, as she wrote daily year after year, keeping the diaries, though she seldom looked at them.

“A.M.—Talked to Mrs. H. Elliot about country neighbours. She knows the Manns; also the Selby-Carroways. How small the world is! Like her. Read a chapter of Miss Appleby’s Adventure to Aunt E. P.M.—Played lawn-tennis with Mr. Perrott and Evelyn M. Don’t like Mr. P. Have a feeling that he is not ‘quite,’ though clever certainly. Beat them. Day splendid, view wonderful. One gets used to no trees, though much too bare at first. Cards after dinner. Aunt E. cheerful, though twingy, she says. Mem.: ask about damp sheets.”

She knelt in prayer, and then lay down in bed, tucking the blankets comfortably about her, and in a few minutes her breathing showed that she was asleep. With its profoundly peaceful sighs and hesitations it resembled that of a cow standing up to its knees all night through in the long grass.

A glance into the next room revealed little more than a nose, prominent above the sheets. Growing accustomed to the darkness, for the windows were open and showed grey squares with splinters of starlight, one could distinguish a lean form, terribly like the body of a dead person, the body indeed of William Pepper, asleep too. Thirty-six, thirty-seven, thirty-eight—here were three Portuguese men of business, asleep presumably, since a snore came with the regularity of a great ticking clock. Thirty-nine was a corner room, at the end of the passage, but late though it was—“One” struck gently downstairs—a line of light under the door showed that some one was still awake.

“How late you are, Hugh!” a woman, lying in bed, said in a peevish but solicitous voice. Her husband was brushing his teeth, and for some moments did not answer.

“You should have gone to sleep,” he replied. “I was talking to Thornbury.”

“But you know that I never can sleep when I’m waiting for you,” she said.

To that he made no answer, but only remarked, “Well then, we’ll turn out the light.” They were silent.

The faint but penetrating pulse of an electric bell could now be heard in the corridor. Old Mrs. Paley, having woken hungry but without her spectacles, was summoning her maid to find the biscuit-box. The maid having answered the bell, drearily respectful even at this hour though muffled in a mackintosh, the passage was left in silence. Downstairs all was empty and dark; but on the upper floor a light still burnt in the room where the boots had dropped so heavily above Miss Allan’s head. Here was the gentleman who, a few hours previously, in the shade of the curtain, had seemed to consist entirely of legs. Deep in an arm-chair he was reading the third volume of Gibbon’s History of the Decline and Fall of Rome by candle-light. As he read he knocked the ash automatically, now and again, from his cigarette and turned the page, while a whole procession of splendid sentences entered his capacious brow and went marching through his brain in order. It seemed likely that this process might continue for an hour or more, until the entire regiment had shifted its quarters, had not the door opened, and the young man, who was inclined to be stout, come in with large naked feet.

“Oh, Hirst, what I forgot to say was—”

“Two minutes,” said Hirst, raising his finger.

He safely stowed away the last words of the paragraph.

“What was it you forgot to say?” he asked.

“D’you think you do make enough allowance for feelings?” asked Mr. Hewet. He had again forgotten what he had meant to say.

After intense contemplation of the immaculate Gibbon Mr. Hirst smiled at the question of his friend. He laid aside his book and considered.

“I should call yours a singularly untidy mind,” he observed. “Feelings? Aren’t they just what we do allow for? We put love up there, and all the rest somewhere down below.” With his left hand he indicated the top of a pyramid, and with his right the base.

“But you didn’t get out of bed to tell me that,” he added severely.

“I got out of bed,” said Hewet vaguely, “merely to talk I suppose.”

“Meanwhile I shall undress,” said Hirst. When naked of all but his shirt, and bent over the basin, Mr. Hirst no longer impressed one with the majesty of his intellect, but with the pathos of his young yet ugly body, for he stooped, and he was so thin that there were dark lines between the different bones of his neck and shoulders.

“Women interest me,” said Hewet, who, sitting on the bed with his chin resting on his knees, paid no attention to the undressing of Mr. Hirst.

“They’re so stupid,” said Hirst. “You’re sitting on my pyjamas.”

“I suppose they are stupid?” Hewet wondered.

“There can’t be two opinions about that, I imagine,” said Hirst, hopping briskly across the room, “unless you’re in love—that fat woman Warrington?” he enquired.

“Not one fat woman—all fat women,” Hewet sighed.

“The women I saw to-night were not fat,” said Hirst, who was taking advantage of Hewet’s company to cut his toe-nails.

“Describe them,” said Hewet.

“You know I can’t describe things!” said Hirst. “They were much like other women, I should think. They always are.”

“No; that’s where we differ,” said Hewet. “I say everything’s different. No two people are in the least the same. Take you and me now.”

“So I used to think once,” said Hirst. “But now they’re all types. Don’t take us—take this hotel. You could draw circles round the whole lot of them, and they’d never stray outside.”

(“You can kill a hen by doing that”), Hewet murmured.

“Mr. Hughling Elliot, Mrs. Hughling Elliot, Miss Allan, Mr. and Mrs. Thornbury—one circle,” Hirst continued. “Miss Warrington, Mr. Arthur Venning, Mr. Perrott, Evelyn M. another circle; then there are a whole lot of natives; finally ourselves.”

“Are we all alone in our circle?” asked Hewet.

“Quite alone,” said Hirst. “You try to get out, but you can’t. You only make a mess of things by trying.”

“I’m not a hen in a circle,” said Hewet. “I’m a dove on a tree-top.”

“I wonder if this is what they call an ingrowing toe-nail?” said Hirst, examining the big toe on his left foot.

“I flit from branch to branch,” continued Hewet. “The world is profoundly pleasant.” He lay back on the bed, upon his arms.

“I wonder if it’s really nice to be as vague as you are?” asked Hirst, looking at him. “It’s the lack of continuity—that’s what’s so odd bout you,” he went on. “At the age of twenty-seven, which is nearly thirty, you seem to have drawn no conclusions. A party of old women excites you still as though you were three.”

Hewet contemplated the angular young man who was neatly brushing the rims of his toe-nails into the fire-place in silence for a moment.

“I respect you, Hirst,” he remarked.

“I envy you—some things,” said Hirst. “One: your capacity for not thinking; two: people like you better than they like me. Women like you, I suppose.”

“I wonder whether that isn’t really what matters most?” said Hewet. Lying now flat on the bed he waved his hand in vague circles above him.

“Of course it is,” said Hirst. “But that’s not the difficulty. The difficulty is, isn’t it, to find an appropriate object?”

“There are no female hens in your circle?” asked Hewet.

“Not the ghost of one,” said Hirst.

Although they had known each other for three years Hirst had never yet heard the true story of Hewet’s loves. In general conversation it was taken for granted that they were many, but in private the subject was allowed to lapse. The fact that he had money enough to do no work, and that he had left Cambridge after two terms owing to a difference with the authorities, and had then travelled and drifted, made his life strange at many points where his friends’ lives were much of a piece.

“I don’t see your circles—I don’t see them,” Hewet continued. “I see a thing like a teetotum spinning in and out—knocking into things—dashing from side to side—collecting numbers—more and more and more, till the whole place is thick with them. Round and round they go—out there, over the rim—out of sight.”

His fingers showed that the waltzing teetotums had spun over the edge of the counterpane and fallen off the bed into infinity.

“Could you contemplate three weeks alone in this hotel?” asked Hirst, after a moment’s pause.

Hewet proceeded to think.

“The truth of it is that one never is alone, and one never is in company,” he concluded.

“Meaning?” said Hirst.

“Meaning? Oh, something about bubbles—auras—what d’you call ’em? You can’t see my bubble; I can’t see yours; all we see of each other is a speck, like the wick in the middle of that flame. The flame goes about with us everywhere; it’s not ourselves exactly, but what we feel; the world is short, or people mainly; all kinds of people.”

“A nice streaky bubble yours must be!” said Hirst.

“And supposing my bubble could run into some one else’s bubble—”

“And they both burst?” put in Hirst.

“Then—then—then—” pondered Hewet, as if to himself, “it would be an e-nor-mous world,” he said, stretching his arms to their full width, as though even so they could hardly clasp the billowy universe, for when he was with Hirst he always felt unusually sanguine and vague.

“I don’t think you altogether as foolish as I used to, Hewet,” said Hirst. “You don’t know what you mean but you try to say it.”

“But aren’t you enjoying yourself here?” asked Hewet.

“On the whole—yes,” said Hirst. “I like observing people. I like looking at things. This country is amazingly beautiful. Did you notice how the top of the mountain turned yellow to-night? Really we must take our lunch and spend the day out. You’re getting disgustingly fat.” He pointed at the calf of Hewet’s bare leg.

“We’ll get up an expedition,” said Hewet energetically. “We’ll ask the entire hotel. We’ll hire donkeys and—”

“Oh, Lord!” said Hirst, “do shut it! I can see Miss Warrington and Miss Allan and Mrs. Elliot and the rest squatting on the stones and quacking, ‘How jolly!’ ”

“We’ll ask Venning and Perrott and Miss Murgatroyd—every one we can lay hands on,” went on Hewet. “What’s the name of the little old grasshopper with the eyeglasses? Pepper?—Pepper shall lead us.”

“Thank God, you’ll never get the donkeys,” said Hirst.

“I must make a note of that,” said Hewet, slowly dropping his feet to the floor. “Hirst escorts Miss Warrington; Pepper advances alone on a white ass; provisions equally distributed—or shall we hire a mule? The matrons—there’s Mrs. Paley, by Jove!—share a carriage.”

“That’s where you’ll go wrong,” said Hirst. “Putting virgins among matrons.”

“How long should you think that an expedition like that would take, Hirst?” asked Hewet.

“From twelve to sixteen hours I would say,” said Hirst. “The time usually occupied by a first confinement.”

“It will need considerable organisation,” said Hewet. He was now padding softly round the room, and stopped to stir the books on the table. They lay heaped one upon another.

“We shall want some poets too,” he remarked. “Not Gibbon; no; d’you happen to have Modern Love or John Donne? You see, I contemplate pauses when people get tired of looking at the view, and then it would be nice to read something rather difficult aloud.”

“Mrs. Paley will enjoy herself,” said Hirst.

“Mrs. Paley will enjoy it certainly,” said Hewet. “It’s one of the saddest things I know—the way elderly ladies cease to read poetry. And yet how appropriate this is:

I speak as one who plumbs
Life’s dim profound,
One who at length can sound
Clear views and certain.
But—after love what comes?
A scene that lours,
A few sad vacant hours,
And then, the Curtain.

I daresay Mrs. Paley is the only one of us who can really understand that.”

“We’ll ask her,” said Hirst. “Please, Hewet, if you must go to bed, draw my curtain. Few things distress me more than the moonlight.”

Hewet retreated, pressing the poems of Thomas Hardy beneath his arm, and in their beds next door to each other both the young men were soon asleep.

Between the extinction of Hewet’s candle and the rising of a dusky Spanish boy who was the first to survey the desolation of the hotel in the early morning, a few hours of silence intervened. One could almost hear a hundred people breathing deeply, and however wakeful and restless it would have been hard to escape sleep in the middle of so much sleep. Looking out of the windows, there was only darkness to be seen. All over the shadowed half of the world people lay prone, and a few flickering lights in empty streets marked the places where their cities were built. Red and yellow omnibuses were crowding each other in Piccadilly; sumptuous women were rocking at a standstill; but here in the darkness an owl flitted from tree to tree, and when the breeze lifted the branches the moon flashed as if it were a torch. Until all people should awake again the houseless animals were abroad, the tigers and the stags, and the elephants coming down in the darkness to drink at pools. The wind at night blowing over the hills and woods was purer and fresher than the wind by day, and the earth, robbed of detail, more mysterious than the earth coloured and divided by roads and fields. For six hours this profound beauty existed, and then as the east grew whiter and whiter the ground swam to the surface, the roads were revealed, the smoke rose and the people stirred, and the sun shone upon the windows of the hotel at Santa Marina until they were uncurtained, and the gong blaring all through the house gave notice of breakfast.

Directly breakfast was over, the ladies as usual circled vaguely, picking up papers and putting them down again, about the hall.

“And what are you going to do to-day?” asked Mrs. Elliot drifting up against Miss Warrington.

Mrs. Elliot, the wife of Hughling the Oxford Don, was a short woman, whose expression was habitually plaintive. Her eyes moved from thing to thing as though they never found anything sufficiently pleasant to rest upon for any length of time.

“I’m going to try to get Aunt Emma out into the town,” said Susan. “She’s not seen a thing yet.”

“I call it so spirited of her at her age,” said Mrs. Elliot, “coming all this way from her own fireside.”

“Yes, we always tell her she’ll die on board ship,” Susan replied. “She was born on one,” she added.

“In the old days,” said Mrs. Elliot, “a great many people were. I always pity the poor women so! We’ve got a lot to complain of!” She shook her head. Her eyes wandered about the table, and she remarked irrelevantly, “The poor little Queen of Holland! Newspaper reporters practically, one may say, at her bedroom door!”

“Were you talking of the Queen of Holland?” said the pleasant voice of Miss Allan, who was searching for the thick pages of The Times among a litter of thin foreign sheets.

“I always envy any one who lives in such an excessively flat country,” she remarked.

“How very strange!” said Mrs. Elliot. “I find a flat country so depressing.”

“I’m afraid you can’t be very happy here then, Miss Allan,” said Susan.

“On the contrary,” said Miss Allan, “I am exceedingly fond of mountains.” Perceiving The Times at some distance, she moved off to secure it.

“Well, I must find my husband,” said Mrs. Elliot, fidgeting away.

“And I must go to my aunt,” said Miss Warrington, and taking up the duties of the day they moved away.

Whether the flimsiness of foreign sheets and the coarseness of their type is any proof of frivolity and ignorance, there is no doubt that English people scarce consider news read there as news, any more than a programme bought from a man in the street inspires confidence in what it says. A very respectable elderly pair, having inspected the long tables of newspapers, did not think it worth their while to read more than the headlines.

“The debate on the fifteenth should have reached us by now,” Mrs. Thornbury murmured. Mr. Thornbury, who was beautifully clean and had red rubbed into his handsome worn face like traces of paint on a weather-beaten wooden figure, looked over his glasses and saw that Miss Allan had The Times.

The couple therefore sat themselves down in arm-chairs and waited.

“Ah, there’s Mr. Hewet,” said Mrs. Thornbury. “Mr. Hewet,” she continued, “do come and sit by us. I was telling my husband how much you reminded me of a dear old friend of mine—Mary Umpleby. She was a most delightful woman, I assure you. She grew roses. We used to stay with her in the old days.”

“No young man likes to have it said that he resembles an elderly spinster,” said Mr. Thornbury.

“On the contrary,” said Mr. Hewet, “I always think it a compliment to remind people of some one else. But Miss Umpleby—why did she grow roses?”

“Ah, poor thing,” said Mrs. Thornbury, “that’s a long story. She had gone through dreadful sorrows. At one time I think she would have lost her senses if it hadn’t been for her garden. The soil was very much against her—a blessing in disguise; she had to be up at dawn—out in all weathers. And then there are creatures that eat roses. But she triumphed. She always did. She was a brave soul.” She sighed deeply but at the same time with resignation.

“I did not realise that I was monopolising the paper,” said Miss Allan, coming up to them.

“We were so anxious to read about the debate,” said Mrs. Thornbury, accepting it on behalf of her husband.

“One doesn’t realise how interesting a debate can be until one has sons in the navy. My interests are equally balanced, though; I have sons in the army too; and one son who makes speeches at the Union—my baby!”

“Hirst would know him, I expect,” said Hewet.

“Mr. Hirst has such an interesting face,” said Mrs. Thornbury. “But I feel one ought to be very clever to talk to him. Well, William?” she enquired, for Mr. Thornbury grunted.

“They’re making a mess of it,” said Mr. Thornbury. He had reached the second column of the report, a spasmodic column, for the Irish members had been brawling three weeks ago at Westminster over a question of naval efficiency. After a disturbed paragraph or two, the column of print once more ran smoothly.

“You have read it?” Mrs. Thornbury asked Miss Allan.

“No, I am ashamed to say I have only read about the discoveries in Crete,” said Miss Allan.

“Oh, but I would give so much to realise the ancient world!” cried Mrs. Thornbury. “Now that we old people are alone—we’re on our second honeymoon—I am really going to put myself to school again. After all we are founded on the past, aren’t we, Mr. Hewet? My soldier son says that there is still a great deal to be learnt from Hannibal. One ought to know so much more than one does. Somehow when I read the paper, I begin with the debates first, and, before I’ve done, the door always opens—we’re a very large party at home—and so one never does think enough about the ancients and all they’ve done for us. But you begin at the beginning, Miss Allan.”

“When I think of the Greeks I think of them as naked black men,” said Miss Allan, “which is quite incorrect, I’m sure.”

“And you, Mr. Hirst?” said Mrs. Thornbury, perceiving that the gaunt young man was near. “I’m sure you read everything.”

“I confine myself to cricket and crime,” said Hirst. “The worst of coming from the upper classes,” he continued, “is that one’s friends are never killed in railway accidents.”

Mr. Thornbury threw down the paper, and emphatically dropped his eyeglasses. The sheets fell in the middle of the group, and were eyed by them all.

“It’s not gone well?” asked his wife solicitously.

Hewet picked up one sheet and read, “A lady was walking yesterday in the streets of Westminster when she perceived a cat in the window of a deserted house. The famished animal—”

“I shall be out of it anyway,” Mr. Thornbury interrupted peevishly.

“Cats are often forgotten,” Miss Allan remarked.

“Remember, William, the Prime Minister has reserved his answer,” said Mrs. Thornbury.

“At the age of eighty, Mr. Joshua Harris of Eeles Park, Brondesbury, has had a son,” said Hirst.

“… The famished animal, which had been noticed by workmen for some days, was rescued, but—by Jove! it bit the man’s hand to pieces!”

“Wild with hunger, I suppose,” commented Miss Allan.

“You’re all neglecting the chief advantage of being abroad,” said Mr. Hughling Elliot, who had joined the group. “You might read your news in French, which is equivalent to reading no news at all.”

Mr. Elliot had a profound knowledge of Coptic, which he concealed as far as possible, and quoted French phrases so exquisitely that it was hard to believe that he could also speak the ordinary tongue. He had an immense respect for the French.

“Coming?” he asked the two young men. “We ought to start before it’s really hot.”

“I beg of you not to walk in the heat, Hugh,” his wife pleaded, giving him an angular parcel enclosing half a chicken and some raisins.

“Hewet will be our barometer,” said Mr. Elliot. “He will melt before I shall.” Indeed, if so much as a drop had melted off his spare ribs, the bones would have lain bare. The ladies were left alone now, surrounding The Times which lay upon the floor. Miss Allan looked at her father’s watch.

“Ten minutes to eleven,” she observed.

“Work?” asked Mrs. Thornbury.

“Work,” replied Miss Allan.

“What a fine creature she is!” murmured Mrs. Thornbury, as the square figure in its manly coat withdrew.

“And I’m sure she has a hard life,” sighed Mrs. Elliot.

“Oh, it is a hard life,” said Mrs. Thornbury. “Unmarried women—earning their livings—it’s the hardest life of all.”

“Yet she seems pretty cheerful,” said Mrs. Elliot.

“It must be very interesting,” said Mrs. Thornbury. “I envy her her knowledge.”

“But that isn’t what women want,” said Mrs. Elliot.

“I’m afraid it’s all a great many can hope to have,” sighed Mrs. Thornbury. “I believe that there are more of us than ever now. Sir Harley Lethbridge was telling me only the other day how difficult it is to find boys for the navy—partly because of their teeth, it is true. And I have heard young women talk quite openly of—”

“Dreadful, dreadful!” exclaimed Mrs. Elliot. “The crown, as one may call it, of a woman’s life. I, who know what it is to be childless—” she sighed and ceased.

“But we must not be hard,” said Mrs. Thornbury. “The conditions are so much changed since I was a young woman.”

“Surely maternity does not change,” said Mrs. Elliot.

“In some ways we can learn a great deal from the young,” said Mrs. Thornbury. “I learn so much from my own daughters.”

“I believe that Hughling really doesn’t mind,” said Mrs. Elliot. “But then he has his work.”

“Women without children can do so much for the children of others,” observed Mrs. Thornbury gently.

“I sketch a great deal,” said Mrs. Elliot, “but that isn’t really an occupation. It’s so disconcerting to find girls just beginning doing better than one does oneself! And nature’s difficult—very difficult!”

“Are there not institutions—clubs—that you could help?” asked Mrs. Thornbury.

“They are so exhausting,” said Mrs. Elliot. “I look strong, because of my colour; but I’m not; the youngest of eleven never is.”

“If the mother is careful before,” said Mrs. Thornbury judicially, “there is no reason why the size of the family should make any difference. And there is no training like the training that brothers and sisters give each other. I am sure of that. I have seen it with my own children. My eldest boy Ralph, for instance—”

But Mrs. Elliot was inattentive to the elder lady’s experience, and her eyes wandered about the hall.

“My mother had two miscarriages, I know,” she said suddenly. “The first because she met one of those great dancing bears—they shouldn’t be allowed; the other—it was a horrid story—our cook had a child and there was a dinner party. So I put my dyspepsia down to that.”

“And a miscarriage is so much worse than a confinement,” Mrs. Thornbury murmured absentmindedly, adjusting her spectacles and picking up The Times. Mrs. Elliot rose and fluttered away.

When she had heard what one of the million voices speaking in the paper had to say, and noticed that a cousin of hers had married a clergyman at Minehead—ignoring the drunken women, the golden animals of Crete, the movements of battalions, the dinners, the reforms, the fires, the indignant, the learned and benevolent, Mrs. Thornbury went upstairs to write a letter for the mail.

The paper lay directly beneath the clock, the two together seeming to represent stability in a changing world. Mr. Perrott passed through; Mr. Venning poised for a second on the edge of a table. Mrs. Paley was wheeled past. Susan followed. Mr. Venning strolled after her. Portuguese military families, their clothes suggesting late rising in untidy bedrooms, trailed across, attended by confidential nurses carrying noisy children. As midday drew on, and the sun beat straight upon the roof, an eddy of great flies droned in a circle; iced drinks were served under the palms; the long blinds were pulled down with a shriek, turning all the light yellow. The clock now had a silent hall to tick in, and an audience of four or five somnolent merchants. By degrees white figures with shady hats came in at the door, admitting a wedge of the hot summer day, and shutting it out again. After resting in the dimness for a minute, they went upstairs. Simultaneously, the clock wheezed one, and the gong sounded, beginning softly, working itself into a frenzy, and ceasing. There was a pause. Then all those who had gone upstairs came down; cripples came, planting both feet on the same step lest they should slip; prim little girls came, holding the nurse’s finger; fat old men came still buttoning waistcoats. The gong had been sounded in the garden, and by degrees recumbent figures rose and strolled in to eat, since the time had come for them to feed again. There were pools and bars of shade in the garden even at midday, where two or three visitors could lie working or talking at their ease.

Owing to the heat of the day, luncheon was generally a silent meal, when people observed their neighbors and took stock of any new faces there might be, hazarding guesses as to who they were and what they did. Mrs. Paley, although well over seventy and crippled in the legs, enjoyed her food and the peculiarities of her fellow-beings. She was seated at a small table with Susan.

“I shouldn’t like to say what she is!” she chuckled, surveying a tall woman dressed conspicuously in white, with paint in the hollows of her cheeks, who was always late, and always attended by a shabby female follower, at which remark Susan blushed, and wondered why her aunt said such things.

Lunch went on methodically, until each of the seven courses was left in fragments and the fruit was merely a toy, to be peeled and sliced as a child destroys a daisy, petal by petal. The food served as an extinguisher upon any faint flame of the human spirit that might survive the midday heat, but Susan sat in her room afterwards, turning over and over the delightful fact that Mr. Venning had come to her in the garden, and had sat there quite half an hour while she read aloud to her aunt. Men and women sought different corners where they could lie unobserved, and from two to four it might be said without exaggeration that the hotel was inhabited by bodies without souls. Disastrous would have been the result if a fire or a death had suddenly demanded something heroic of human nature, but tragedies come in the hungry hours. Towards four o’clock the human spirit again began to lick the body, as a flame licks a black promontory of coal. Mrs. Paley felt it unseemly to open her toothless jaw so widely, though there was no one near, and Mrs. Elliot surveyed her found flushed face anxiously in the looking-glass.

Half an hour later, having removed the traces of sleep, they met each other in the hall, and Mrs. Paley observed that she was going to have her tea.

“You like your tea too, don’t you?” she said, and invited Mrs. Elliot, whose husband was still out, to join her at a special table which she had placed for her under a tree.

“A little silver goes a long way in this country,” she chuckled.

She sent Susan back to fetch another cup.

“They have such excellent biscuits here,” she said, contemplating a plateful. “Not sweet biscuits, which I don’t like—dry biscuits … Have you been sketching?”

“Oh, I’ve done two or three little daubs,” said Mrs. Elliot, speaking rather louder than usual. “But it’s so difficult after Oxfordshire, where there are so many trees. The light’s so strong here. Some people admire it, I know, but I find it very fatiguing.”

“I really don’t need cooking, Susan,” said Mrs. Paley, when her niece returned. “I must trouble you to move me.” Everything had to be moved. Finally the old lady was placed so that the light wavered over her, as though she were a fish in a net. Susan poured out tea, and was just remarking that they were having hot weather in Wiltshire too, when Mr. Venning asked whether he might join them.

“It’s so nice to find a young man who doesn’t despise tea,” said Mrs. Paley, regaining her good humour. “One of my nephews the other day asked for a glass of sherry—at five o’clock! I told him he could get it at the public house round the corner, but not in my drawing room.”

“I’d rather go without lunch than tea,” said Mr. Venning. “That’s not strictly true. I want both.”

Mr. Venning was a dark young man, about thirty-two years of age, very slapdash and confident in his manner, although at this moment obviously a little excited. His friend Mr. Perrott was a barrister, and as Mr. Perrott refused to go anywhere without Mr. Venning it was necessary, when Mr. Perrott came to Santa Marina about a Company, for Mr. Venning to come too. He was a barrister also, but he loathed a profession which kept him indoors over books, and directly his widowed mother died he was going, so he confided to Susan, to take up flying seriously, and become partner in a large business for making aeroplanes. The talk rambled on. It dealt, of course, with the beauties and singularities of the place, the streets, the people, and the quantities of unowned yellow dogs.

“Don’t you think it dreadfully cruel the way they treat dogs in this country?” asked Mrs. Paley.

“I’d have ’em all shot,” said Mr. Venning.

“Oh, but the darling puppies,” said Susan.

“Jolly little chaps,” said Mr. Venning. “Look here, you’ve got nothing to eat.” A great wedge of cake was handed Susan on the point of a trembling knife. Her hand trembled too as she took it.

“I have such a dear dog at home,” said Mrs. Elliot.

“My parrot can’t stand dogs,” said Mrs. Paley, with the air of one making a confidence. “I always suspect that he (or she) was teased by a dog when I was abroad.”

“You didn’t get far this morning, Miss Warrington,” said Mr. Venning.

“It was hot,” she answered. Their conversation became private, owing to Mrs. Paley’s deafness and the long sad history which Mrs. Elliot had embarked upon of a wire-haired terrier, white with just one black spot, belonging to an uncle of hers, which had committed suicide. “Animals do commit suicide,” she sighed, as if she asserted a painful fact.

“Couldn’t we explore the town this evening?” Mr. Venning suggested.

“My aunt—” Susan began.

“You deserve a holiday,” he said. “You’re always doing things for other people.”

“But that’s my life,” she said, under cover of refilling the teapot.

“That’s no one’s life,” he returned, “no young person’s. You’ll come?”

“I should like to come,” she murmured.

At this moment Mrs. Elliot looked up and exclaimed, “Oh, Hugh! He’s bringing some one,” she added.

“He would like some tea,” said Mrs. Paley. “Susan, run and get some cups—there are the two young men.”

“We’re thirsting for tea,” said Mr. Elliot. “You know Mr. Ambrose, Hilda? We met on the hill.”

“He dragged me in,” said Ridley, “or I should have been ashamed. I’m dusty and dirty and disagreeable.” He pointed to his boots which were white with dust, while a dejected flower drooping in his buttonhole, like an exhausted animal over a gate, added to the effect of length and untidiness. He was introduced to the others. Mr. Hewet and Mr. Hirst brought chairs, and tea began again, Susan pouring cascades of water from pot to pot, always cheerfully, and with the competence of long use.

“My wife’s brother,” Ridley explained to Hilda, whom he failed to remember, “has a house here, which he has lent us. I was sitting on a rock thinking of nothing at all when Elliot started up like a fairy in a pantomime.”

“Our chicken got into the salt,” Hewet said dolefully to Susan. “Nor is it true that bananas include moisture as well as sustenance.”

Hirst was already drinking.

“We’ve been cursing you,” said Ridley in answer to Mrs. Elliot’s kind enquiries about his wife. “You tourists eat up all the eggs, Helen tells me. That’s an eye-sore too”—he nodded his head at the hotel. “Disgusting luxury, I call it. We live with pigs in the drawing-room.”

“The food is not at all what it ought to be, considering the price,” said Mrs. Paley seriously. “But unless one goes to a hotel where is one to go to?”

“Stay at home,” said Ridley. “I often wish I had! Everyone ought to stay at home. But, of course, they won’t.”

Mrs. Paley conceived a certain grudge against Ridley, who seemed to be criticising her habits after an acquaintance of five minutes.

“I believe in foreign travel myself,” she stated, “if one knows one’s native land, which I think I can honestly say I do. I should not allow any one to travel until they had visited Kent and Dorsetshire—Kent for the hops, and Dorsetshire for its old stone cottages. There is nothing to compare with them here.”

“Yes—I always think that some people like the flat and other people like the downs,” said Mrs. Elliot rather vaguely.

Hirst, who had been eating and drinking without interruption, now lit a cigarette, and observed, “Oh, but we’re all agreed by this time that nature’s a mistake. She’s either very ugly, appallingly uncomfortable, or absolutely terrifying. I don’t know which alarms me most—a cow or a tree. I once met a cow in a field by night. The creature looked at me. I assure you it turned my hair grey. It’s a disgrace that the animals should be allowed to go at large.”

“And what did the cow think of him?” Venning mumbled to Susan, who immediately decided in her own mind that Mr. Hirst was a dreadful young man, and that although he had such an air of being clever he probably wasn’t as clever as Arthur, in the ways that really matter.

“Wasn’t it Wilde who discovered the fact that nature makes no allowance for hip-bones?” enquired Hughling Elliot. He knew by this time exactly what scholarships and distinction Hirst enjoyed, and had formed a very high opinion of his capacities.

But Hirst merely drew his lips together very tightly and made no reply.

Ridley conjectured that it was now permissible for him to take his leave. Politeness required him to thank Mrs. Elliot for his tea, and to add, with a wave of his hand, “You must come up and see us.”

The wave included both Hirst and Hewet, and Hewet answered, “I should like it immensely.”

The party broke up, and Susan, who had never felt so happy in her life, was just about to start for her walk in the town with Arthur, when Mrs. Paley beckoned her back. She could not understand from the book how Double Demon patience is played; and suggested that if they sat down and worked it out together it would fill up the time nicely before dinner.

XI

One after another they rose and stretched themselves, and in a few minutes divided more or less into two separate parties. One of these parties was dominated by Hughling Elliot and Mrs.¬ÝThornbury, who, having both read the same books and considered the same questions, were now anxious to name the places beneath them and to hang upon them stores of information about navies and armies, political parties, natives and mineral products‚ÅÝ‚Äîall of which combined, they said, to prove that South America was the country of the future.

Evelyn M. listened with her bright blue eyes fixed upon the oracles.

‚ÄúHow it makes one long to be a man!‚Äù she exclaimed.

Mr.¬ÝPerrott answered, surveying the plain, that a country with a future was a very fine thing.

‚ÄúIf I were you,‚Äù said Evelyn, turning to him and drawing her glove vehemently through her fingers, ‚ÄúI‚Äôd raise a troop and conquer some great territory and make it splendid. You‚Äôd want women for that. I‚Äôd love to start life from the very beginning as it ought to be‚ÅÝ‚Äînothing squalid‚ÅÝ‚Äîbut great halls and gardens and splendid men and women. But you‚ÅÝ‚Äîyou only like Law Courts!‚Äù

‚ÄúAnd would you really be content without pretty frocks and sweets and all the things young ladies like?‚Äù asked Mr.¬ÝPerrott, concealing a certain amount of pain beneath his ironical manner.

‚ÄúI‚Äôm not a young lady,‚Äù Evelyn flashed; she bit her underlip. ‚ÄúJust because I like splendid things you laugh at me. Why are there no men like Garibaldi now?‚Äù she demanded.

‚ÄúLook here,‚Äù said Mr.¬ÝPerrott, ‚Äúyou don‚Äôt give me a chance. You think we ought to begin things fresh. Good. But I don‚Äôt see precisely‚ÅÝ‚Äîconquer a territory? They‚Äôre all conquered already, aren‚Äôt they?‚Äù

‚ÄúIt‚Äôs not any territory in particular,‚Äù Evelyn explained. ‚ÄúIt‚Äôs the idea, don‚Äôt you see? We lead such tame lives. And I feel sure you‚Äôve got splendid things in you.‚Äù

Hewet saw the scars and hollows in Mr.¬ÝPerrott‚Äôs sagacious face relax pathetically. He could imagine the calculations which even then went on within his mind, as to whether he would be justified in asking a woman to marry him, considering that he made no more than five hundred a year at the Bar, owned no private means, and had an invalid sister to support. Mr.¬ÝPerrott again knew that he was not ‚Äúquite,‚Äù as Susan stated in her diary; not quite a gentleman she meant, for he was the son of a grocer in Leeds, had started life with a basket on his back, and now, though practically indistinguishable from a born gentleman, showed his origin to keen eyes in an impeccable neatness of dress, lack of freedom in manner, extreme cleanliness of person, and a certain indescribable timidity and precision with his knife and fork which might be the relic of days when meat was rare, and the way of handling it by no means gingerly.

The two parties who were strolling about and losing their unity now came together, and joined each other in a long stare over the yellow and green patches of the heated landscape below. The hot air danced across it, making it impossible to see the roofs of a village on the plain distinctly. Even on the top of the mountain where a breeze played lightly, it was very hot, and the heat, the food, the immense space, and perhaps some less well-defined cause produced a comfortable drowsiness and a sense of happy relaxation in them. They did not say much, but felt no constraint in being silent.

‚ÄúSuppose we go and see what‚Äôs to be seen over there?‚Äù said Arthur to Susan, and the pair walked off together, their departure certainly sending some thrill of emotion through the rest.

‚ÄúAn odd lot, aren‚Äôt they?‚Äù said Arthur. ‚ÄúI thought we should never get ‚Äôem all to the top. But I‚Äôm glad we came, by Jove! I wouldn‚Äôt have missed this for something.‚Äù

‚ÄúI don‚Äôt like Mr.¬ÝHirst,‚Äù said Susan inconsequently. ‚ÄúI suppose he‚Äôs very clever, but why should clever people be so‚ÅÝ‚ÄîI expect he‚Äôs awfully nice, really,‚Äù she added, instinctively qualifying what might have seemed an unkind remark.

‚ÄúHirst? Oh, he‚Äôs one of these learned chaps,‚Äù said Arthur indifferently. ‚ÄúHe don‚Äôt look as if he enjoyed it. You should hear him talking to Elliot. It‚Äôs as much as I can do to follow ‚Äôem at all.‚ÅÝ‚Ää‚ÅÝ‚Ä¶ I was never good at my books.‚Äù

With these sentences and the pauses that came between them they reached a little hillock, on the top of which grew several slim trees.

‚ÄúD‚Äôyou mind if we sit down here?‚Äù said Arthur, looking about him. ‚ÄúIt‚Äôs jolly in the shade‚ÅÝ‚Äîand the view‚ÅÝ‚Äî‚Äù They sat down, and looked straight ahead of them in silence for some time.

‚ÄúBut I do envy those clever chaps sometimes,‚Äù Arthur remarked. ‚ÄúI don‚Äôt suppose they ever‚ÅÝ‚Ää‚ÅÝ‚Ä¶‚Äù He did not finish his sentence.

‚ÄúI can‚Äôt see why you should envy them,‚Äù said Susan, with great sincerity.

‚ÄúOdd things happen to one,‚Äù said Arthur. ‚ÄúOne goes along smoothly enough, one thing following another, and it‚Äôs all very jolly and plain sailing, and you think you know all about it, and suddenly one doesn‚Äôt know where one is a bit, and everything seems different from what it used to seem. Now today, coming up that path, riding behind you, I seemed to see everything as if‚ÅÝ‚Äî‚Äù he paused and plucked a piece of grass up by the roots. He scattered the little lumps of earth which were sticking to the roots‚ÅÝ‚Äî‚ÄúAs if it had a kind of meaning. You‚Äôve made the difference to me,‚Äù he jerked out, ‚ÄúI don‚Äôt see why I shouldn‚Äôt tell you. I‚Äôve felt it ever since I knew you.‚ÅÝ‚Ää‚ÅÝ‚Ä¶ It‚Äôs because I love you.‚Äù

Even while they had been saying commonplace things Susan had been conscious of the excitement of intimacy, which seemed not only to lay bare something in her, but in the trees and the sky, and the progress of his speech which seemed inevitable was positively painful to her, for no human being had ever come so close to her before.

She was struck motionless as his speech went on, and her heart gave great separate leaps at the last words. She sat with her fingers curled round a stone, looking straight in front of her down the mountain over the plain. So then, it had actually happened to her, a proposal of marriage.

Arthur looked round at her; his face was oddly twisted. She was drawing her breath with such difficulty that she could hardly answer.

‚ÄúYou might have known.‚Äù He seized her in his arms; again and again and again they clasped each other, murmuring inarticulately.

‚ÄúWell,‚Äù sighed Arthur, sinking back on the ground, ‚Äúthat‚Äôs the most wonderful thing that‚Äôs ever happened to me.‚Äù He looked as if he were trying to put things seen in a dream beside real things.

There was a long silence.

‚ÄúIt‚Äôs the most perfect thing in the world,‚Äù Susan stated, very gently and with great conviction. It was no longer merely a proposal of marriage, but of marriage with Arthur, with whom she was in love.

In the silence that followed, holding his hand tightly in hers, she prayed to God that she might make him a good wife.

‚ÄúAnd what will Mr.¬ÝPerrott say?‚Äù she asked at the end of it.

‚ÄúDear old fellow,‚Äù said Arthur who, now that the first shock was over, was relaxing into an enormous sense of pleasure and contentment. ‚ÄúWe must be very nice to him, Susan.‚Äù

He told her how hard Perrott‚Äôs life had been, and how absurdly devoted he was to Arthur himself. He went on to tell her about his mother, a widow lady, of strong character. In return Susan sketched the portraits of her own family‚ÅÝ‚ÄîEdith in particular, her youngest sister, whom she loved better than anyone else, ‚Äúexcept you, Arthur.‚ÅÝ‚Ää‚ÅÝ‚Ä¶ Arthur,‚Äù she continued, ‚Äúwhat was it that you first liked me for?‚Äù

‚ÄúIt was a buckle you wore one night at sea,‚Äù said Arthur, after due consideration. ‚ÄúI remember noticing‚ÅÝ‚Äîit‚Äôs an absurd thing to notice!‚ÅÝ‚Äîthat you didn‚Äôt take peas, because I don‚Äôt either.‚Äù

From this they went on to compare their more serious tastes, or rather Susan ascertained what Arthur cared about, and professed herself very fond of the same thing. They would live in London, perhaps have a cottage in the country near Susan‚Äôs family, for they would find it strange without her at first. Her mind, stunned to begin with, now flew to the various changes that her engagement would make‚ÅÝ‚Äîhow delightful it would be to join the ranks of the married women‚ÅÝ‚Äîno longer to hang on to groups of girls much younger than herself‚ÅÝ‚Äîto escape the long solitude of an old maid‚Äôs life. Now and then her amazing good fortune overcame her, and she turned to Arthur with an exclamation of love.

They lay in each other‚Äôs arms and had no notion that they were observed. Yet two figures suddenly appeared among the trees above them. ‚ÄúHere‚Äôs shade,‚Äù began Hewet, when Rachel suddenly stopped dead. They saw a man and woman lying on the ground beneath them, rolling slightly this way and that as the embrace tightened and slackened. The man then sat upright and the woman, who now appeared to be Susan Warrington, lay back upon the ground, with her eyes shut and an absorbed look upon her face, as though she were not altogether conscious. Nor could you tell from her expression whether she was happy, or had suffered something. When Arthur again turned to her, butting her as a lamb butts a ewe, Hewet and Rachel retreated without a word. Hewet felt uncomfortably shy.

‚ÄúI don‚Äôt like that,‚Äù said Rachel after a moment.

‚ÄúI can remember not liking it either,‚Äù said Hewet. ‚ÄúI can remember‚ÅÝ‚Äî‚Äù but he changed his mind and continued in an ordinary tone of voice, ‚ÄúWell, we may take it for granted that they‚Äôre engaged. D‚Äôyou think he‚Äôll ever fly, or will she put a stop to that?‚Äù

But Rachel was still agitated; she could not get away from the sight they had just seen. Instead of answering Hewet she persisted.

‚ÄúLove‚Äôs an odd thing, isn‚Äôt it, making one‚Äôs heart beat.‚Äù

‚ÄúIt‚Äôs so enormously important, you see,‚Äù Hewet replied. ‚ÄúTheir lives are now changed forever.‚Äù

‚ÄúAnd it makes one sorry for them too,‚Äù Rachel continued, as though she were tracing the course of her feelings. ‚ÄúI don‚Äôt know either of them, but I could almost burst into tears. That‚Äôs silly, isn‚Äôt it?‚Äù

‚ÄúJust because they‚Äôre in love,‚Äù said Hewet. ‚ÄúYes,‚Äù he added after a moment‚Äôs consideration, ‚Äúthere‚Äôs something horribly pathetic about it, I agree.‚Äù

And now, as they had walked some way from the grove of trees, and had come to a rounded hollow very tempting to the back, they proceeded to sit down, and the impression of the lovers lost some of its force, though a certain intensity of vision, which was probably the result of the sight, remained with them. As a day upon which any emotion has been repressed is different from other days, so this day was now different, merely because they had seen other people at a crisis of their lives.

‚ÄúA great encampment of tents they might be,‚Äù said Hewet, looking in front of him at the mountains. ‚ÄúIsn‚Äôt it like a watercolour too‚ÅÝ‚Äîyou know the way watercolours dry in ridges all across the paper‚ÅÝ‚ÄîI‚Äôve been wondering what they looked like.‚Äù

His eyes became dreamy, as though he were matching things, and reminded Rachel in their colour of the green flesh of a snail. She sat beside him looking at the mountains too. When it became painful to look any longer, the great size of the view seeming to enlarge her eyes beyond their natural limit, she looked at the ground; it pleased her to scrutinise this inch of the soil of South America so minutely that she noticed every grain of earth and made it into a world where she was endowed with the supreme power. She bent a blade of grass, and set an insect on the utmost tassel of it, and wondered if the insect realised his strange adventure, and thought how strange it was that she should have bent that tassel rather than any other of the million tassels.

‚ÄúYou‚Äôve never told me your name,‚Äù said Hewet suddenly. ‚ÄúMiss Somebody Vinrace.‚ÅÝ‚Ää‚ÅÝ‚Ä¶ I like to know people‚Äôs Christian names.‚Äù

‚ÄúRachel,‚Äù she replied.

‚ÄúRachel,‚Äù he repeated. ‚ÄúI have an aunt called Rachel, who put the life of Father Damien into verse. She is a religious fanatic‚ÅÝ‚Äîthe result of the way she was brought up, down in Northamptonshire, never seeing a soul. Have you any aunts?‚Äù

‚ÄúI live with them,‚Äù said Rachel.

‚ÄúAnd I wonder what they‚Äôre doing now?‚Äù Hewet enquired.

‚ÄúThey are probably buying wool,‚Äù Rachel determined. She tried to describe them. ‚ÄúThey are small, rather pale women,‚Äù she began, ‚Äúvery clean. We live in Richmond. They have an old dog, too, who will only eat the marrow out of bones.‚ÅÝ‚Ää‚ÅÝ‚Ä¶ They are always going to church. They tidy their drawers a good deal.‚Äù But here she was overcome by the difficulty of describing people.

‚ÄúIt‚Äôs impossible to believe that it‚Äôs all going on still!‚Äù she exclaimed.

The sun was behind them and two long shadows suddenly lay upon the ground in front of them, one waving because it was made by a skirt, and the other stationary, because thrown by a pair of legs in trousers.

‚ÄúYou look very comfortable!‚Äù said Helen‚Äôs voice above them.

‚ÄúHirst,‚Äù said Hewet, pointing at the scissorlike shadow; he then rolled round to look up at them.

‚ÄúThere‚Äôs room for us all here,‚Äù he said.

When Hirst had seated himself comfortably, he said:

‚ÄúDid you congratulate the young couple?‚Äù

It appeared that, coming to the same spot a few minutes after Hewet and Rachel, Helen and Hirst had seen precisely the same thing.

‚ÄúNo, we didn‚Äôt congratulate them,‚Äù said Hewet. ‚ÄúThey seemed very happy.‚Äù

‚ÄúWell,‚Äù said Hirst, pursing up his lips, ‚Äúso long as I needn‚Äôt marry either of them‚ÅÝ‚Äî‚Äù

‚ÄúWe were very much moved,‚Äù said Hewet.

‚ÄúI thought you would be,‚Äù said Hirst. ‚ÄúWhich was it, Monk? The thought of the immortal passions, or the thought of newborn males to keep the Roman Catholics out? I assure you,‚Äù he said to Helen, ‚Äúhe‚Äôs capable of being moved by either.‚Äù

Rachel was a good deal stung by his banter, which she felt to be directed equally against them both, but she could think of no repartee.

‚ÄúNothing moves Hirst,‚Äù Hewet laughed; he did not seem to be stung at all. ‚ÄúUnless it were a transfinite number falling in love with a finite one‚ÅÝ‚ÄîI suppose such things do happen, even in mathematics.‚Äù

‚ÄúOn the contrary,‚Äù said Hirst with a touch of annoyance, ‚ÄúI consider myself a person of very strong passions.‚Äù It was clear from the way he spoke that he meant it seriously; he spoke of course for the benefit of the ladies.

‚ÄúBy the way, Hirst,‚Äù said Hewet, after a pause, ‚ÄúI have a terrible confession to make. Your book‚ÅÝ‚Äîthe poems of Wordsworth, which if you remember I took off your table just as we were starting, and certainly put in my pocket here‚ÅÝ‚Äî‚Äù

‚ÄúIs lost,‚Äù Hirst finished for him.

‚ÄúI consider that there is still a chance,‚Äù Hewet urged, slapping himself to right and left, ‚Äúthat I never did take it after all.‚Äù

‚ÄúNo,‚Äù said Hirst. ‚ÄúIt is here.‚Äù He pointed to his breast.

‚ÄúThank God,‚Äù Hewet exclaimed. ‚ÄúI need no longer feel as though I‚Äôd murdered a child!‚Äù

‚ÄúI should think you were always losing things,‚Äù Helen remarked, looking at him meditatively.

‚ÄúI don‚Äôt lose things,‚Äù said Hewet. ‚ÄúI mislay them. That was the reason why Hirst refused to share a cabin with me on the voyage out.‚Äù

‚ÄúYou came out together?‚Äù Helen enquired.

‚ÄúI propose that each member of this party now gives a short biographical sketch of himself or herself,‚Äù said Hirst, sitting upright. ‚ÄúMiss Vinrace, you come first; begin.‚Äù

Rachel stated that she was twenty-four years of age, the daughter of a shipowner, that she had never been properly educated; played the piano, had no brothers or sisters, and lived at Richmond with aunts, her mother being dead.

‚ÄúNext,‚Äù said Hirst, having taken in these facts; he pointed at Hewet. ‚ÄúI am the son of an English gentleman. I am twenty-seven,‚Äù Hewet began. ‚ÄúMy father was a foxhunting squire. He died when I was ten in the hunting field. I can remember his body coming home, on a shutter I suppose, just as I was going down to tea, and noticing that there was jam for tea, and wondering whether I should be allowed‚ÅÝ‚Äî‚Äù

‚ÄúYes; but keep to the facts,‚Äù Hirst put in.

‚ÄúI was educated at Winchester and Cambridge, which I had to leave after a time. I have done a good many things since‚ÅÝ‚Äî‚Äù

‚ÄúProfession?‚Äù

‚ÄúNone‚ÅÝ‚Äîat least‚ÅÝ‚Äî‚Äù

‚ÄúTastes?‚Äù

‚ÄúLiterary. I‚Äôm writing a novel.‚Äù

‚ÄúBrothers and sisters?‚Äù

‚ÄúThree sisters, no brother, and a mother.‚Äù

‚ÄúIs that all we‚Äôre to hear about you?‚Äù said Helen. She stated that she was very old‚ÅÝ‚Äîforty last October, and her father had been a solicitor in the city who had gone bankrupt, for which reason she had never had much education‚ÅÝ‚Äîthey lived in one place after another‚ÅÝ‚Äîbut an elder brother used to lend her books.

‚ÄúIf I were to tell you everything‚ÅÝ‚Äî‚Äù she stopped and smiled. ‚ÄúIt would take too long,‚Äù she concluded. ‚ÄúI married when I was thirty, and I have two children. My husband is a scholar. And now‚ÅÝ‚Äîit‚Äôs your turn,‚Äù she nodded at Hirst.

‚ÄúYou‚Äôve left out a great deal,‚Äù he reproved her. ‚ÄúMy name is St.¬ÝJohn Alaric Hirst,‚Äù he began in a jaunty tone of voice. ‚ÄúI‚Äôm twenty-four years old. I‚Äôm the son of the Reverend Sidney Hirst, vicar of Great Wappyng in Norfolk. Oh, I got scholarships everywhere‚ÅÝ‚ÄîWestminster‚ÅÝ‚ÄîKing‚Äôs. I‚Äôm now a fellow of King‚Äôs. Don‚Äôt it sound dreary? Parents both alive (alas). Two brothers and one sister. I‚Äôm a very distinguished young man,‚Äù he added.

‚ÄúOne of the three, or is it five, most distinguished men in England,‚Äù Hewet remarked.

‚ÄúQuite correct,‚Äù said Hirst.

‚ÄúThat‚Äôs all very interesting,‚Äù said Helen after a pause. ‚ÄúBut of course we‚Äôve left out the only questions that matter. For instance, are we Christians?‚Äù

‚ÄúI am not,‚Äù ‚ÄúI am not,‚Äù both the young men replied.

‚ÄúI am,‚Äù Rachel stated.

‚ÄúYou believe in a personal God?‚Äù Hirst demanded, turning round and fixing her with his eyeglasses.

‚ÄúI believe‚ÅÝ‚ÄîI believe,‚Äù Rachel stammered, ‚ÄúI believe there are things we don‚Äôt know about, and the world might change in a minute and anything appear.‚Äù

At this Helen laughed outright. ‚ÄúNonsense,‚Äù she said. ‚ÄúYou‚Äôre not a Christian. You‚Äôve never thought what you are.‚ÅÝ‚ÄîAnd there are lots of other questions,‚Äù she continued, ‚Äúthough perhaps we can‚Äôt ask them yet.‚Äù Although they had talked so freely they were all uncomfortably conscious that they really knew nothing about each other.

‚ÄúThe important questions,‚Äù Hewet pondered, ‚Äúthe really interesting ones. I doubt that one ever does ask them.‚Äù

Rachel, who was slow to accept the fact that only a very few things can be said even by people who know each other well, insisted on knowing what he meant.

‚ÄúWhether we‚Äôve ever been in love?‚Äù she enquired. ‚ÄúIs that the kind of question you mean?‚Äù

Again Helen laughed at her, benignantly strewing her with handfuls of the long tasselled grass, for she was so brave and so foolish.

‚ÄúOh, Rachel,‚Äù she cried. ‚ÄúIt‚Äôs like having a puppy in the house having you with one‚ÅÝ‚Äîa puppy that brings one‚Äôs underclothes down into the hall.‚Äù

But again the sunny earth in front of them was crossed by fantastic wavering figures, the shadows of men and women.

‚ÄúThere they are!‚Äù exclaimed Mrs.¬ÝElliot. There was a touch of peevishness in her voice. ‚ÄúAnd we‚Äôve had such a hunt to find you. Do you know what the time is?‚Äù

Mrs.¬ÝElliot and Mr.¬Ýand Mrs.¬ÝThornbury now confronted them; Mrs.¬ÝElliot was holding out her watch, and playfully tapping it upon the face. Hewet was recalled to the fact that this was a party for which he was responsible, and he immediately led them back to the watchtower, where they were to have tea before starting home again. A bright crimson scarf fluttered from the top of the wall, which Mr.¬ÝPerrott and Evelyn were tying to a stone as the others came up. The heat had changed just so far that instead of sitting in the shadow they sat in the sun, which was still hot enough to paint their faces red and yellow, and to colour great sections of the earth beneath them.

‚ÄúThere‚Äôs nothing half so nice as tea!‚Äù said Mrs.¬ÝThornbury, taking her cup.

‚ÄúNothing,‚Äù said Helen. ‚ÄúCan‚Äôt you remember as a child chopping up hay‚ÅÝ‚Äî‚Äù she spoke much more quickly than usual, and kept her eye fixed upon Mrs.¬ÝThornbury, ‚Äúand pretending it was tea, and getting scolded by the nurses‚ÅÝ‚Äîwhy I can‚Äôt imagine, except that nurses are such brutes, won‚Äôt allow pepper instead of salt though there‚Äôs no earthly harm in it. Weren‚Äôt your nurses just the same?‚Äù

During this speech Susan came into the group, and sat down by Helen‚Äôs side. A few minutes later Mr.¬ÝVenning strolled up from the opposite direction. He was a little flushed, and in the mood to answer hilariously whatever was said to him.

‚ÄúWhat have you been doing to that old chap‚Äôs grave?‚Äù he asked, pointing to the red flag which floated from the top of the stones.

‚ÄúWe have tried to make him forget his misfortune in having died three hundred years ago,‚Äù said Mr.¬ÝPerrott.

‚ÄúIt would be awful‚ÅÝ‚Äîto be dead!‚Äù ejaculated Evelyn M.

‚ÄúTo be dead?‚Äù said Hewet. ‚ÄúI don‚Äôt think it would be awful. It‚Äôs quite easy to imagine. When you go to bed tonight fold your hands so‚ÅÝ‚Äîbreathe slower and slower‚ÅÝ‚Äî‚Äù He lay back with his hands clasped upon his breast, and his eyes shut, ‚ÄúNow,‚Äù he murmured in an even monotonous voice, ‚ÄúI shall never, never, never move again.‚Äù His body, lying flat among them, did for a moment suggest death.

‚ÄúThis is a horrible exhibition, Mr.¬ÝHewet!‚Äù cried Mrs.¬ÝThornbury.

‚ÄúMore cake for us!‚Äù said Arthur.

‚ÄúI assure you there‚Äôs nothing horrible about it,‚Äù said Hewet, sitting up and laying hands upon the cake.

‚ÄúIt‚Äôs so natural,‚Äù he repeated. ‚ÄúPeople with children should make them do that exercise every night.‚ÅÝ‚Ää‚ÅÝ‚Ä¶ Not that I look forward to being dead.‚Äù

‚ÄúAnd when you allude to a grave,‚Äù said Mr.¬ÝThornbury, who spoke almost for the first time, ‚Äúhave you any authority for calling that ruin a grave? I am quite with you in refusing to accept the common interpretation which declares it to be the remains of an Elizabethan watchtower‚ÅÝ‚Äîany more than I believe that the circular mounds or barrows which we find on the top of our English downs were camps. The antiquaries call everything a camp. I am always asking them, Well then, where do you think our ancestors kept their cattle? Half the camps in England are merely the ancient pound or barton as we call it in my part of the world. The argument that no one would keep his cattle in such exposed and inaccessible spots has no weight at all, if you reflect that in those days a man‚Äôs cattle were his capital, his stock-in-trade, his daughter‚Äôs dowries. Without cattle he was a serf, another man‚Äôs man.‚ÅÝ‚Ää‚ÅÝ‚Ä¶‚Äù His eyes slowly lost their intensity, and he muttered a few concluding words under his breath, looking curiously old and forlorn.

Hughling Elliot, who might have been expected to engage the old gentleman in argument, was absent at the moment. He now came up holding out a large square of cotton upon which a fine design was printed in pleasant bright colours that made his hand look pale.

‚ÄúA bargain,‚Äù he announced, laying it down on the cloth. ‚ÄúI‚Äôve just bought it from the big man with the earrings. Fine, isn‚Äôt it? It wouldn‚Äôt suit everyone, of course, but it‚Äôs just the thing‚ÅÝ‚Äîisn‚Äôt it, Hilda?‚ÅÝ‚Äîfor Mrs.¬ÝRaymond Parry.‚Äù

‚ÄúMrs.¬ÝRaymond Parry!‚Äù cried Helen and Mrs.¬ÝThornbury at the same moment.

They looked at each other as though a mist hitherto obscuring their faces had been blown away.

‚ÄúAh‚ÅÝ‚Äîyou have been to those wonderful parties too?‚Äù Mrs.¬ÝElliot asked with interest.

Mrs.¬ÝParry‚Äôs drawing-room, though thousands of miles away, behind a vast curve of water on a tiny piece of earth, came before their eyes. They who had had no solidity or anchorage before seemed to be attached to it somehow, and at once grown more substantial. Perhaps they had been in the drawing-room at the same moment; perhaps they had passed each other on the stairs; at any rate they knew some of the same people. They looked one another up and down with new interest. But they could do no more than look at each other, for there was no time to enjoy the fruits of the discovery. The donkeys were advancing, and it was advisable to begin the descent immediately, for the night fell so quickly that it would be dark before they were home again.

Accordingly, remounting in order, they filed off down the hillside. Scraps of talk came floating back from one to another. There were jokes to begin with, and laughter; some walked part of the way, and picked flowers, and sent stones bounding before them.

‚ÄúWho writes the best Latin verse in your college, Hirst?‚Äù Mr.¬ÝElliot called back incongruously, and Mr.¬ÝHirst returned that he had no idea.

The dusk fell as suddenly as the natives had warned them, the hollows of the mountain on either side filling up with darkness and the path becoming so dim that it was surprising to hear the donkeys‚Äô hooves still striking on hard rock. Silence fell upon one, and then upon another, until they were all silent, their minds spilling out into the deep blue air. The way seemed shorter in the dark than in the day; and soon the lights of the town were seen on the flat far beneath them.

Suddenly someone cried, ‚ÄúAh!‚Äù

In a moment the slow yellow drop rose again from the plain below; it rose, paused, opened like a flower, and fell in a shower of drops.

‚ÄúFireworks,‚Äù they cried.

Another went up more quickly; and then another; they could almost hear it twist and roar.

‚ÄúSome Saint‚Äôs day, I suppose,‚Äù said a voice. The rush and embrace of the rockets as they soared up into the air seemed like the fiery way in which lovers suddenly rose and united, leaving the crowd gazing up at them with strained white faces. But Susan and Arthur, riding down the hill, never said a word to each other, and kept accurately apart.

Then the fireworks became erratic, and soon they ceased altogether, and the rest of the journey was made almost in darkness, the mountain being a great shadow behind them, and bushes and trees little shadows which threw darkness across the road. Among the plane-trees they separated, bundling into carriages and driving off, without saying good night, or saying it only in a half-muffled way.

It was so late that there was no time for normal conversation between their arrival at the hotel and their retirement to bed. But Hirst wandered into Hewet‚Äôs room with a collar in his hand.

‚ÄúWell, Hewet,‚Äù he remarked, on the crest of a gigantic yawn, ‚Äúthat was a great success, I consider.‚Äù He yawned. ‚ÄúBut take care you‚Äôre not landed with that young woman.‚ÅÝ‚Ää‚ÅÝ‚Ä¶ I don‚Äôt really like young women.‚ÅÝ‚Ää‚ÅÝ‚Ä¶‚Äù

Hewet was too much drugged by hours in the open air to make any reply. In fact every one of the party was sound asleep within ten minutes or so of each other, with the exception of Susan Warrington. She lay for a considerable time looking blankly at the wall opposite, her hands clasped above her heart, and her light burning by her side. All articulate thought had long ago deserted her; her heart seemed to have grown to the size of a sun, and to illuminate her entire body, shedding like the sun a steady tide of warmth.

‚ÄúI‚Äôm happy, I‚Äôm happy, I‚Äôm happy,‚Äù she repeated. ‚ÄúI love every one. I‚Äôm happy.‚Äù